so let's get started well it's really a
lot of people in here so thanks for
coming all and thanks for having me and
today I want to present to your PDF
chairs and one of you or let's see how
many of you heard of protech already
okay not that much so it's gonna be more
to introduce that's cool so here's what
I want to do a little bit of overview
and I got 50 minute walk in and what you
give you something like background on
how PDFs are structured how we process
them into only PDF chairs and then go to
some of ya the hex we do to get images
and fonts working and then face the
thing or showed problems we face in some
steps we want to do in the future and
then to do a small demo at the end so
what does PDF is all about well it's
nothing else than just building an
awesome TF fewer in your web browser and
it's just using html5 technologies so
it's really isn't experimenting where
can you push the web platform where
people will say well PDF or a No can you
do this on the web is it fast enough and
this is just project Z well actually we
can we don't use native code if you want
to see how far we come this year is a
keynote presentation export to PDF and
brought to you by PDF chairs so we
already got something working butter sub
stuff to do so one of the reasons
besides being cool and having all
running in your browser is also security
so if you think of it a lot of people
download PDFs nowadays from the internet
and just open them in there and they're
Acrobat Reader so for some flaws you
might think you're secure and what you
get back from server you can just open
but you never can trust and even SSL can
be attacked as we know now so if you
just run everything in this really small
sandbox in your browser
nothing can attach
or attack you Oh SST so there was this
article on heist news and also and I got
this just before so this is a chart how
windows get affected which are the main
programs as you see most a 32% get em
attacked by Crowe Acrobat Reader so if
they got a not up-to-date version or
whatever so see this is really something
important and by using just web
technologies
you just have JavaScript and nothing can
explore ok so now let's go a little bit
more in default um so how is PDF
structured to give you a background to
see later on how we process it well at
bottom and at the top we got a header
which is most still interest to version
of PDF there multiple versions and then
the biggest chunk is the body the body
is something like a sequence of objects
an object in PDF semantic could be
anything like it can contains fonts that
are embedded in PDF ok contain drawing
commands like draw a line here and then
rectangle there or add some text to this
in that position image data words
bookmarks form feels any kind of
information more a button we get em
something like a mapping between objects
IDs and by its offset as you see we got
something to do because some font
encoding is not working right now VHS
and so this allows you to say ok I want
you have object number 12 and it and if
you don't have this reference you would
have to go through the entire PDF stream
and figure out where up check number 12
starts but with this extra reference
table you can say okay object number 12
starts offset 200 so I just got to seek
unto a 200 and read from there as you
know how long an object is really can
just make sure you just only this one
object and one you got a trailer which
contain the word object
ie which is the derivative checked holes
and all the pages such that you know
okay I go to this object and this object
shows all the idea is to connect objects
they got to read if I want to go to page
five or something and the cool thing
about the structures you can create PDFs
in one fly because all the the chunk
tables a setter is at the end and you
can jump around in PDF document so if
you just got an object ID just can go to
any offset and read from there so now
see how this works in PDF chairs so at
first point and you make an exchange or
two requests to get some data is a
charger compared to xhrs something the
same but you can say I want you have
typed array back so what you get back is
richest a big chunk or wide array that
you can process over and we put a three
month that all streams and coding and
stuff is all headed in JavaScript then
we create a new PDF document around a
stream and we read X reference table
such that we know where each object is
referent M is pointed in the data stream
and read the root object and then we say
well we want to have page n okay we'll
get patron they will say well we will
just stay out rendering and we pass in
graphics object and the graphics object
is what later on knows how to deal with
the painting chrome ads that we sent to
it internally just call start rendering
and you read and convert all the PDF
commands that are in there we see the
later in trade and I are for and that's
done in the partial over what we call
partial evaluator and we make sure that
all the required objects like phones and
images are loaded because if you try to
set a font on the canvas and you try to
treat render it before it's not loaded
you just get nothing so you don't want
you have that and then once we are
insured and we have all completely are
we say okay correctly execute our IR and
you get something painted and generally
we have canvas beckoned
so that's confirmed by canvas crafts
so let's go even a bit more even if we
say for example okay PDF document we
want to have get page and let's say okay
and it should have integer so let's say
we want to have the first page it says
okay you got to go to object number
three so this is what object number
three look like actually it's real I
kiss if you open your PDF document
sometimes it's compressed so you don't
see the content in this readable format
but basically it's reaches the set of
commands
so you see object number three its type
of page we know how big it is
we know where the resources are that
object number four we know depend and we
know the confidence object on five so we
want to process object number four and
object number five when we want to
render so this is now what object number
five will apply we know okay so here we
know it's length eight and it's a stream
and as a side stream might be encoded
and just in this case it's plain text
little bit more easier and you already
see there are some kinds of commands
like yeah begin text move somewhere show
some text and we go see us later
okay now int only as I said we fetch
already your resources and now we got
this thing right we and together with
our extra friends catalog which is this
root object thing and resource that we
load we bring it to the partial
evaluator which creates Ohio art form
this is what the current I all looks
like so you see em most of the commands
just get expanded and um PDF puts the
name of the commands at the back and we
have them in front and just the
parameters just become all as from are
you missed any put your function calls
or you also sort of do some
transformations for example this one
here on left hand side and PDF means
okay set the current font to font zero
which is a reference to resources and
use em
number 12 internally we mark-1 zero
which is fun zero in our object space we
load it and once it's loaded we resolve
promise and the dependency we add to tie
our make sure we don't come across this
point until the font is resolved so what
happens we say okay execute IR we go
through all the commands and we say ok
there's the dependency we check if the
dependence is satisfied which isn't
satisfied yet we stall the execution
wait until it's satisfied and continue
the execution again by doing this we can
later on split up processing of the PDF
because you can think okay I got font
that's required I gather image that's
required so I can send object for an
image to web broker which one does that
thing in front you not a web worker and
once everything is there so today I can
continue execution it's going to happen
and this ir form is then passed to
canvas graphics which change the actual
writing okay so this was more or less
the technical stuff was that too hard or
the questions raising internal
representation so if you just the
problem is in this form if you just take
this you got em still reference to
objects they're ideas that the ir don't
have dependencies on am streams or
things anymore such that if you move
some chunk of data to worker and it
sends something back that's an ir form
you don't have to get access to data in
so that's why make transformation also
to add in the defensive stuff and
there's um the PDF document can also
have something like nested PDF documents
where it says okay this is a year is a
formula again and you get to go to
another trick interesting processing as
well and we've them flat there so then
which is animal for my own extreme
other questions
okay so now two and technial things I
want to have a little bit more details
so how do you load images and to render
them in Gaza well so in PDF documents
the two different kinds you can shape
extreme
well that's question well you just read
some bytes you convert in and then you
create a Dom object and you set a source
to data you are and once it's loaded you
say okay I can use it well if it's not
JPEG stream and there can be a different
color spaces in PDF or sever and
sometimes it's just like you've got some
bite and then you got okay it is this
grayscale but I got to have four colors
all four red blue green m3 okay okay so
we got to make this conversion ourself
so what we do we read the bytes we
convert into color space we take some
image shade off the right size from the
scratch canvas we fill the pixel data on
the canvas then we put it in which data
on the canvas again and we draw an
entire canvas on our PDF cannons so you
see this is really a lot of work but
it's still performs quite well so next
things are fonts there are two ways you
could Halla phones one is rendering each
character with drawing commands so if
you got an A and you have something like
this you've draw one line you more line
here or the other option is transforming
fonts and a lot of different ones and
SSA ones are still not really supported
at all edges and there's some formats
that we don't support all the way we do
it is we take the PDF fonts that are
embedded and convert into OpenType fonts
then again we use CSS to attach them to
the dom and once it's loaded we start
rendering because if you say I want to
use the font and it's not loaded yet you
might end up with whitespace there's
problem that sample
Scannell converted to open types or at
least not that simple and we don't know
yet what we one do there so maybe these
ones got to be drawn read one by drop
okay so now let's face some problems
that we have and in fallen I'm going to
use platform for browser bustle it's
combination so there's actually no real
way to detect people fund is loaded
there are things like okay we can see if
the whiff of something changes or if
there's some output but there are really
edge cases where you just have white em
just in space so if you want to say well
if just something drawn then you
unloaded but if you have a white space
you don't see anything drawn and also
there are some edge case with with so we
got something act like we load curl the
font in iframe and if the iframe says
I'm loaded we hope that an airframe has
fun loaded as well and say it's loaded
but that's not working on WebKit in some
situations and font with so um some
fonts may pour different size then it
actually should be so if you render it
in Firefox on some platforms it ends up
positioning them at the wrong place so
currently we got to paint every check
turn on its and on the calculate
position to make sure it get right and
sub fun them our sub pixel font size is
not working on some platforms that's
also why we draw each character like all
text selection is not working because we
just use canvas so we got some text but
yeah you can tree select it printing is
also problem because can we just draw a
canvas and if you say okay just have
print and you remove some of the UI of
your PF you end up with this low res
that canvas and think that is sent to
your printer which is if you expect at
least one DP you way to you
hello so there are two ways either we
create a realign canvas or we might want
to use SVG and sure speed got to be
better and we want to achieve this by
using workers
did some work on this direction but it's
not landed yet and also we could maybe
do something like partial rendering
where's okay I got this part of document
ready I'll just start rendering and
there's maybe sub formula that isn't
already and or nothing
not everything to render stare at this
point but maybe if most of the text is
there and just a slogan is missing it's
better than just holding on to
everything is there so here's a list of
traduz that came up so let's say there's
more fun work we got to figure out
sprinting speed and we got to support
more of the rendering spec so what we
have actually allows us to cover a lot
of PDF documents but there're a lot of
edge cases like you can have PostScript
embedded as some functions in PDF and
some weird shading and they'll get to
get implement and also we might want to
explore Azra tree and how slow is it how
fast is it if we get SOG working we get
around text selection because we have
text there then we can select in also
printing there's the point and there's a
back on micellar that you can select a
switch a right now but people working
with this ed and then there are more
advanced features than just rendering so
you can have PDF formulas or three in
each graphic and crazy stuff and PDF
forms or something might look in the
future and the more at one stuff got to
see outfits and also from an
infrastructure point and someone that's
got hired from the sellers working on
automated testing environment such that
you can say PDF chairs but please start
testing it makes a poor form from pull
requests and checks all PDFs that we've
got and make reference tests and see if
something changed a lot and also true
only the entire code base is more or
less and all transcripts start so
everything just goes to global space so
we want might want to have something
like a why I just cleaned it up and also
we want to test more PDF documents
because it's hard to implement specs if
you don't have test object so if you
want to help in a very simple way
computing code please open one or two
PDF documents that I come across of even
more and if something play playfully get
help in shape okay so any more time
any questions so far yeah yes yes so
what we do currently we got some URLs or
PDFs on the web we just pull in and
basically each time someone comes up
with problem we ask him politely can put
it somewhere that we can pull in or
copyright is okay when you just move it
in repo yes so it's all a little yes
there was also the idea and the most of
all hands in meeting that we could use
being search and say well give us the
100 or 1000 most probably a few PDF
pages and hope that copywriters are okay
with that pull it in the repo and see if
that works
so some kind of that yes so search isn't
working right now and well I mean we
know where we rendered the photo where
we ended text so we could keep that in
mind something and it's not working
right now
so definitely feature to implement but
what we have is links and such that if
you go over some text in a click on it
goes to not page that's what you know
okay
Oh where's I go to themes
so this one here is what I'll start with
so some reason it doesn't thing up to it
sighs sorry
so this is the first first and document
we had so trace marker paper and enter s
call start this project and the
implement trace monkey form and the
seller and for Firefox so that's why
choose this block document and there are
some graphics in there you see there's
quite some stuff already working when
you see it's kind of lagging whenever
it's reaching in your page you hold you
I fridges and stuff that's because
everything single threaded right now so
especially here takes quite some time so
yeah so we hope we get a better with
them he's working also if you got really
trying PDF
[Music]
so for example if you take and the PDF
em well let's documentation that's a way
of why Adobe and that's 32 megabyte and
you can extend ya think if you've got to
render all over this it's gonna take
some time
yes what you continue but once it's
there is and the first time the font is
loaded because font loading is really
going over all the bits making sure they
are open type step now you see here you
can jump here and we just jump to the
place allotment and if the page is small
is just text the speed is already quite
useful but yeah they're rendering bugs
so a lot so M as I said the cool thing
is in theory you would just store in the
data and then read some parts of the
object and what you also could do is say
well so maybe you'll be polite in for
just one tap this range of data just
send it to me
so saying is server supports that you
can you can't do right now but there is
an EM draft to make accessor arches say
I want this range of M by I to the M of
fights and that way you can prevent
darling 32 megabytes maybe but that's
not working right now yes
so
so and maybe I repeated questions the
question was if you can use HTML and CSS
just for texturing and stuff and if you
think of it there's something like
sliding a SlideShare
let's go like it in Crocodoc which
allows you uploading more or less new
PDF slides and they can worry to HTML so
it's possible to do that and we got to
explore our classes and there's some so
the problem there is and what can happen
in PDF is you got some text and you got
some graphics above and then some text
again but I don't know how big this
graph is going to be so you would need
to spin a canvas for the entire document
again what can happen if there's a
little bit of text and try and carrying
a little bit of text right cameras so
would you use a lot of memory it's
technologies cameras above and I think
the PDF renderer on the web that
converts to text and CSS that just say
all Kravis go to the background I will
put text on top so if you have some
graphics that cover the text it won't
work because it just puts it down that
we want to have for doing working so get
to see yes
so I think the main PFR and PHS files
around 300k and our stuff without
compression so it's quite huge if you
got to implement all this and different
streams and yeah it's a little bit of
code okay yeah but we haven't yeah we
don't get that much working as David oh
yes sir
so um so I'm actually a student at ETH
and studying physics and I was at
Mozilla two weeks ago hacking on PDF
chess
so we're read and mad andreas on the
racks of team and currently things are
like a mentor as is making some code
reviews and get some good input but he's
working on boot to gecko retina and
Chris Jones who was at first time with
Chris and the country is working on this
is on boot to gecko as well this are now
two full employees working for muscle on
the project one on test infrastructure
when I got implemented the PF renderer
as well and so he hide a competitor and
there's one contractor and a few and
contributors so quite a few
and maybe that's good one so I got two
euro to contact so get up page my Lingus
and IRC if you got any questions if you
have PDF that's not working and I hope
and you get so there's getting started
thing that there's online demo that you
can check out so you just want Tessa
thanks break a lot this is easy square
to go and there's also how you can clone
stuff and make us server running okay so
thanks for listening and have a good one
[Applause]